[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's the same line we're talking now.
[SPEAKER_01]: The hindrances we were speaking about the other day.
[SPEAKER_01]: They belong to the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Without...
[SPEAKER_01]: They cannot arise without the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Inseparable from... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the hindrances being... Oh, I forgot what I had to say.
[SPEAKER_01]: Weakness, interruptions of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Weakness of wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's always at the first, you know, if you can abandon those.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know if it means to destroy those.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Arahant fully goes beyond hindrance, whereby any any hindrance that arises, it's not a hindrance for him, because his mind is beyond that, or above it, so they don't.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they're still...
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no, it's not a hindrance there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Say the body has moods.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bodily existence of the five aggregates has moods.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that mood is taking you.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's throwing you about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because your mind is somewhere wedged in between.
[SPEAKER_00]: Weak and confused in regard to it and appropriating it as mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: For another one, it's completely free.
[SPEAKER_00]: Free from any appropriation, any conceiving, whatever else.
[SPEAKER_00]: They truly remain just bodily.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, whatever arises, it won't be a hindrance, and it will never develop to the extent that it used to develop, because it used to develop because it was a hindrance, because you did take it as mine, and then revolved around it even more, and proliferated even further.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you got into that mood of whatever here will bust, and then you just... you were taken over by this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, and then it becomes mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: But like lust, for example, it takes a while, like sexual desire, for example, it takes a while before it becomes a full-on sexual desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when I say it takes a while, I mean it takes some time of attending it wrongly,
[SPEAKER_00]: Giving attention to the sound of beauty, getting wound up, getting excited.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, yeah, then you can be in that state perpetually.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or state of ill-will.
[SPEAKER_00]: But nevertheless, they take time to develop.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, that developing means this kind of revolving, when you don't escape from the initial itch of sexual desire, which is purely bodily.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because for as long as there is a body, for as long as there is a prostate, organ, and penis, and everything else, there will be
[SPEAKER_00]: A possibility of an itch.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's all turd.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, the whole significance of the sexual organs, sensuality, and everything else, and the whole appropriation of that, means it's never seen just as an itch.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, sometimes.
[SPEAKER_00]: But again, even when it is, it's seen as my itch.
[SPEAKER_00]: And since there is nothing preventing you from stopping it, from not indulging it, people don't understand the danger of indulging it,
[SPEAKER_00]: They do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe not physically, but they do it mentally.
[SPEAKER_00]: They nurture it, they cherish it, they entertain it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You give in to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might be resisting, but let's say a layman, yeah, you fully lay your plank.
[SPEAKER_00]: You take on the reins, not just... you go for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it was purely bodily.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it always remains inseparable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Imagine if there was no body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Would you be able to experience sexual desire?
[SPEAKER_00]: Imagine if there is no mouth, no tongue, would you be able to enjoy the tasty food?
[SPEAKER_00]: You wouldn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: You couldn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Inseparable from.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, any food that you ever enjoyed, any food that you are enjoying, any food that you will enjoy, is completely bound to your tongue.
[SPEAKER_00]: Literally.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's completely bodily.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of that, it's entirely bodily.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because all of the other permutations can happen, come and go.
[SPEAKER_00]: But this remains as a necessary condition.
[SPEAKER_00]: Presence of a working tongue, working eyes, working ears.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if eyes and what they see would be a problem, if tongue and the taste would be a problem, removing the tongue would remove the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: But none of it is the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your mind is not the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your thoughts are not the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just a craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just a craving in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The assumption that the body is one.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it all comes out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mind and conceit and craving all revolve around the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: You conceive.
[SPEAKER_00]: You take it as yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're taking me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then you become, you know, that which chases after the counterpart.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for as long as you're identifying with your masculine body, masculine sexual organ,
[SPEAKER_00]: masculine possibility of sexual pleasure, of sensual pleasure in general, you will be bound by that pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you are restraining, even if you spend the rest of your life as a celibate restraining, if you don't sever the connection internally, you will... you remain bound, you remain in sensual domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, you're just saying no, but you're not... Yeah, you're not actually freeing yourself from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Saying no is the first step, but it's the first step that can only enable you to see the escape.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not the escape itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I step back in reflection, when I look at the body that appears, in whatever form it appears in,
[SPEAKER_01]: Might be a sensation.
[SPEAKER_00]: The physical breathing or the... See, that's already... your body was already there before.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that sensation was being possible to be manifested because the body was already there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I don't see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're not mindful of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And another reason why you don't see it, is because, for you, only that particular manifestation of this or that, that manifests the body, is the manifestation of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you develop knowledge that actually, any of those particular manifestations are possible only because the body is already there, that thought, the body is already there, starts to stand, begins standing for that which is the body in your experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, that is your body and your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no in-between.
[SPEAKER_01]: The thought that the body is already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, would you be able to think anything above the body, if that body is not standing there?
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can't know it any other way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't access that through the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sensations, sights, sensations of touch, sights, sounds, smell, that's all sensual.
[SPEAKER_00]: That all comes through senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's usually the criteria of
[SPEAKER_00]: What exists, put it in vertical, so existence is much more than that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, but when you know that all those things are possible only because the body is already there, and that body is already there, because you're thinking it, you realize, ah, that's how the mind comes first, because this all precedes it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That thought of the body preceding them is a real thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's your body.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is what your body is, at that level, at that time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, you can go back to the satipaṭṭhāna mindfulness of the bodily postures.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're seated now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your body is in a certain position.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whether you look at it, whether I'm telling you about it, whether you're touching the chair, that's all because you're seated already.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in a sense, that cannot... that the body is seated is a thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, what else would you expect it to be?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because all of the sight, sound, smell, taste and touches are known because they manifest in mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, they're also thoughts that correspond to respective senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: But sense in itself, without the mind, is incomprehensible.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, thoughts that concern your sight are thoughts of your sight.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or of your eye organ, if you want to put it like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why there's six different types of consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's six different types of thoughts, you can say it like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're different.
[SPEAKER_00]: They all appear to be looking the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: But they're bound to different things, thus they're different.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thoughts about a smell?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, it seems just a thought about a smell, or thought about a sight.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seems it's a thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: And yeah, that is in common.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're both thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: They both pertain to the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: But they're different thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: One is bound with the eye organ.
[SPEAKER_00]: Another one is bound with the nose organ.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, a thought of your body being there, mental, is bound with the presence of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: With the sixth sense base.
[SPEAKER_00]: With the entire thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, keeping the thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't even keep it, actually.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how we develop mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not constant keeping in your mind, because it will drive you mad eventually.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's recognizing the different layers of that generality whereby things appear.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have particular things while you're seated on the chair, what you're doing, holding something in your hand, or listening, talking, all of that while you are being seated.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, see, if you forget that you were seated, and then you continue on doing things while you're seated, on one level you lost some mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the thing is, you can remember it in a mindful way that would make your memory mindful.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, you might lose the actual awareness of your, I am seated on this chair, but if halfway through whatever you were doing, you remember, literally remember, that you are still being seated, and that is the anchor, that was the anchor of your mindfulness, that memory becomes mindful.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that which you've done in that, like, time span,
[SPEAKER_00]: When you forgot, and now you remember, that also is rendered mindful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the position of a body thrown in the world, random, existing on its own, given five aggregates, something you can never appropriate, actually.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, your whole experience depends upon it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And mindfulness of bodily postures revealed that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Positioned body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of which I can do, I can think, I can worry, I can be angry, I can be happy, I can be this, I can be that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the... like...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't mean because you're seated.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean because the body is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seated, standing, walking, lying down, is just like a little extra reminder of any body being there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's always the...
[SPEAKER_00]: Those are always the foundations of your experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: No matter how great, or how lowly, or how depressed, or how late your experience might be in general, the fact is, it all requires a body to be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I can recognize the posture, and I can...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you recognize the posture.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the thing is, you can't keep it actual in front of you all the time, because other things will start arising, because that's just how things work.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's not the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everybody can... like, vipassana people, when they're touching, touching, walking, walking, sitting, sitting, they're all recognizing
[SPEAKER_00]: The point is to recognize it and then let it go.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let it go wherever it wants to go.
[SPEAKER_00]: And as long as you don't stand up, you won't lose mindfulness of the fact that you're seated.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't actually have to be trying to be mindful.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're mindful by position... by your body being positioned.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, your body is mindful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is how that mindfulness can let... can... well, can never lapse or lapsing of that mindfulness becomes less and less occurring.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the other one has the supreme mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because even when he forgets, that forgetfulness is mindful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's in regard to particular things.
[SPEAKER_00]: But his body is situated there, in one posture or the other, and that's his mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: The person has to anchor themselves back and back.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, in the beginning, he was earlier seated on the line.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you find yourself, you drift, you drift off.
[SPEAKER_01]: You drift off, yeah, okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all about this.
[SPEAKER_01]: But are you still seated?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then I realize I'm still seated.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, the problem is, with that, people keep overdoing it, because you don't know what you're supposed to achieve.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why I say, understanding mindfulness will make you mindful.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're seated now, and you're mindful that you're seated, and now you drift off.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if, at any point, you'll feel drifted off, I ask you,
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you sitting?
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you sitting or are you seated?
[SPEAKER_00]: You would say yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the knowledge of the body position pertains to the body and it's there with the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why you can afford to forget it, in that mental keeping it in front of me all the time sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: It takes time.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's basically recognizing the peripheral to the extent necessary that things don't
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, to the extent necessary that forgetting particular things doesn't induce general non-mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can put it like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you might have lost a particular thought that I am seated here now, but you are still seated here now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means,
[SPEAKER_00]: Even when you were thinking, I'm seated here now, that wasn't your mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: The fact that you were seated right there and then, that's where your mindfulness was, or could have been.
[SPEAKER_01]: You see, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: If I...
[SPEAKER_01]: From time to time in the day, I say, I sit down and I do something specific meditation, mindfulness of breathing.
[SPEAKER_01]: I say, well, I will, I keep that in mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll be mindful of my breathing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I sit there for a while, but then I get up.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think about this, think about that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then I might say, I'll be mindful of my body posture.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll be mindful of my feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll be mindful of this.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, am I...
[SPEAKER_01]: I feel that I'm aware of my situation, my surroundings, the state of my mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then I have doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I actually being mindful of that particular thing?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I... Well, because you have to find your bodily posture, your breathing, your feelings, whatever you want to be mindful of.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to find that within the general situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not in front of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in that general situation, that's... that's how you have to start.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, within that, without abandoning the... the image of general situation, you have to start discerning feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to start discerning presence of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: In this general situation, if I, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: I... yeah, I feel like in a...
[SPEAKER_01]: I can...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm aware of the general situation, but
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm surrounded by it, in a way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm within it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's empowered, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And whatever I think of as the body, within that, that stands for the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pretty much.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there can be a number of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That will all be... inseparable from a body.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's conceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: It'll be a thought, but always within the general... George, have a thought of general situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if I do have a thought of general situation, is that not making it in front of me?
[SPEAKER_00]: It depends.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether it's going to be in front of you or not, it depends how you attend it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you over-attend it, under-attend it, miss-attend it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't attend it properly...
[SPEAKER_01]: General situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can think behind you.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, if you're behind me, that can become in front of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because must my mind be split?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it doesn't really matter that much, actually.
[SPEAKER_00]: What matters is to develop the sense of the mindfulness of while.
[SPEAKER_00]: The two simultaneous layers, if you want to put it that way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, particularly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the particular is that, or the bodily and mental.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can put it as crudely as that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, obviously, both bodily and mental are mental, in a certain way.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there are mental things that pertain solely to mental, and there are mental things to the bodily.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, mental is split into bodily and mental.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in that sense, everything is... your mind comes first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just without mind, it's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: But not everything is entirely mental.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even the whole thing of body and mind will not be able to stand if there is no body that is conscious out there, but everyone in the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or as you probably say this, the Pali word for situation is vipassana.
[SPEAKER_00]: Vipassana.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's, eh... Yeah, I suppose.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you have to start from the state of puthujjana.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, being contacted, having things manifested, that would be the original situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: By recognizing the original situation, you can eventually go through it, literally, discern through it,
[SPEAKER_00]: Not left, right, above, below.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right through it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you cease to regard it as mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then you're not contacted.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there's still arising.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, puthujjana situation is taunted.
[SPEAKER_00]: But situation will pretend to arising.
[SPEAKER_00]: Arising in passing away of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if that touches you, if you make it mine, then you're contacted by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it doesn't, then you're not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, if the situation, general situation, you said that, that's... About this, before I forget it, because I forgot it once, I want to say.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can induce the mindfulness of a general situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: And while you're mindful of the general situation, let your body do things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Walk, sit, move about.
[SPEAKER_00]: While you're mindful of the general situation,
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that indirect way of seeing that body, not directly doing it, but letting it do, while you're looking at it through the mindful general situation, is one among the bodies.
[SPEAKER_00]: One among the experience of the bodies.
[SPEAKER_01]: Every mindful of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the whole point of ānāpānasati.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through doing breath, you do other things through this thing, which means they'll never be directly done,
[SPEAKER_00]: They'll be indirectly observed while they're done.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what you feel there, what you perceive there, what you do there, is a feeling, is a perception, is something that's well done.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have to start recognizing that indirectly, peripherally, seeing something remotely, still stands for that thing that you're seeing remotely.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just directly in front of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how mindfulness develops.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, while you're mindful of the entire situation,
[SPEAKER_00]: Your body is seated there on its own, almost as if it has its own existence, independent of you and your general situation, so to speak, not entirely.
[SPEAKER_00]: But in a way, yes, because you don't have to be sitting to be seated.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're seated.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there is something the body does, yet you don't have to keep doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same with breathing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can be doing the breathing, but the body is also doing the breathing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you can be mindful of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Breathing as well, while you're mindful of the general situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that... As if, like, because you're mindful of the general situation, you cannot be fully absorbed 100% into breathing or sitting or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_00]: To not be.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because then you start recognizing it indirectly, peripherally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is, again, the reason why this whole vipassana mainstream is completely wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, they believe you can have a hundred percent attention upon the one thing, and you can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the frustration...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think I'm trying... like I said, your mind has to be split, but I'm trying to give a hundred percent to both.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your mind can be split, and then you can be trying to attend that hundred percent.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of all of the different... because of peripheral in general, and infinity on that structure, you can't have one thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or rather, that structure is one thing, but you can't step outside of it, and then attend it as one thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can only see it from within, which means it will always be nāma and rūpa.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let me see one more.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the general situation, being mindful, being aware of it, and particularly those body and feelings,
[SPEAKER_01]: And that awareness of the mindfulness, that's within that situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: As well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is...
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why, if you do it long enough, the belief that you can be outside of that situation will fade.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that belief is sakāyabhid.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whereby your sense of self, your personality, is outside of your experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just assuming.
[SPEAKER_00]: Failing to see that that assumption is within this experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you keep seeing the situation in general, the entire situation, within that, while your mindful situation, in my body, of what you feel or whatever, partially, because you don't want to be fully absorbing what you feel, because you forget about the situation,
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, it becomes apparent that, well, whatever arises within this, will be within this situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you do it long enough, you stop assuming that there can be anything out of the situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because even your assumption is wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever it is, about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is how the sense of self is then recognized peripherally, ambiguously, within that situation, as a phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if it's within that situation, it cannot be the owner of that situation, cannot be the creator, cannot be the master.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you abandon ātavāda like that, which is the belief that your self is far more superior than your whole experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if it's manifested, it's impermanent for a very reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now you see it manifested, means it persists.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you're mindful of the situation...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll stop saying situation as general, because every situation is general.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you're mindful of the situation, and then within that mindfulness of the situation, keep a peripheral eye on what your body is doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: There won't be anything left out, because whatever arises will be between the two, and that's already included in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you get used to that, or rather if you develop it to the insufficient extent, then you can also see that they're mutually determining each other.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your entire situation would not be manifested if this random body is still not alive, sitting on the chair, breathing, being nurtured by food or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_00]: And vice versa.
[SPEAKER_00]: If there is no situation recognized as such, this body will not be manifested at all within.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you can't even imagine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Every... like, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, thinking that that's already the situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: When I was... in terms of the breath, when I was what?
[SPEAKER_01]: When I was, say, attending to the breath, and I tried to attend to that as much as I can,
[SPEAKER_01]: I think you wrote it in your notes on meditation.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just said now, you allow the body and the feelings to arise by themselves, so to speak, to emerge or arise by themselves, so that you don't have to conceive it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they're no longer conceived, they just arise as they do.
[SPEAKER_00]: You recognize they would arise with whether you conceive them or not, which means my conceiving becomes redundant.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, if I'm looking at the... if I'm doing ānāpānasati, like that, or breathing, breathing, breathing, and I'm...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm looking at the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the body arises and I'm like, oh, that's the body, which I'm not supposed to conceive.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, again, you don't conceive it necessarily just by thinking that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, as I said, well, if you do ānāpānasati,
[SPEAKER_00]: Mindfulness of breathing is your situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: I am breathing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's your situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Within that, I'm breathing while the body is like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm breathing while the body is like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm going to breathe in while the body will be like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm going to breathe...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm going to breathe feeling this.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm going to breathe feeling that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you start thinking about the feeling and everything, you can't afford that, if your mindfulness gets developed to such an extent whereby an act of breathing, whether you do it or not, is where it's anchored.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you are still breathing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, when you go back to the breathing, you go back as if it was always there, because it was always there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, your forgetting becomes mind... well, rather, your forgetting becomes within the mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you remember, everything is rendered as mindful memory.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mindful memory means a memory that will not induce a vision.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: What do you mean, not induce a vision?
[SPEAKER_00]: Not, eh... Well, like, an arahant can remember stuff he'd done when he was a contingent.
[SPEAKER_00]: But none of those memories will induce a regeneration.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you forget about the breathing, but then you become mindful of the fact... well, when your body is mindful, but the breathing is still happening, even if you go and think about other things, when you get back to...
[SPEAKER_00]: Or rather, let's put it like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Remembering that you were supposed to be breathing, practicing mindfulness of breathing, that act won't be like, oh, I remember something I forgot.
[SPEAKER_00]: Remembering will just mean bringing you back to the breathing that is already there, and was already there, and was happening all this time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, your mindfulness was already there, was already there, and was happening all this time.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, remembering and forgetting doesn't induce a vijā anymore in regard to where was I, what was I doing, how to start again.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just means going somewhere else and coming back to the other thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is what you do all the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you don't know that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you go somewhere else, you forget.
[SPEAKER_00]: i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: the assumptions of a vijā and everything else, the upādāna, the perpetuate.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can also start from dead breathing, looking at the situation inside.
[SPEAKER_00]: Satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just take any of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can start with any of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either the body's here...
[SPEAKER_00]: But there's so many different types of practicing body markets.
[SPEAKER_00]: Looking at dead corpses.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a form of satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because a corpse, a corpse in regard to which you feel no loss, you feel dispassion, can be conceived without standing for a body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mind, body of others, body of both, internal, external, internal and external.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't, because it's entirely bodily.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in that sense, by being mindful of
[SPEAKER_00]: Attitude of dispersion towards the body, you're mindful of attitude of dispersion towards the nature of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can do that by, again, being mindful of the situation while you're looking at a Subha.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, don't go fully look at a Subha.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, don't give 100% attention and forget which you are and what you're doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're mindful of your situation, and then look at a surah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And keep looking.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's something you're doing, while you're mindful of the situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Within...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, peripherally, you're aware of it, but you don't go full in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then it... then it... As such, you start recognizing it, through that indirect attention, which is not
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's indirect only in relation to what you're used to be with, what you're used to be direct.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's only indirect in relation to that, but in itself, it's just a different form of attending.
[SPEAKER_00]: Peripheral attending.
[SPEAKER_00]: Without over-committing, without fully conceiving, without going there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that body, that dispassion that is manifested at that time, through that peripheral attending, is one of the bodies.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's one of the mantra bodies.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't require you.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't require mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't require doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you've done something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's all to do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you just have to start recognizing it, without taking it up fully.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you'll make sure you won't take it up fully, for as long as you remain mindful.
[SPEAKER_00]: What about, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you can look at awareness, like awareness.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: What situation?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, look yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: My awareness, that's basically my situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: General awareness without anybody, that's my situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, just dwelling in my general awareness, well, that becomes something you actually do, and it becomes a particular thing, which means then the background of it would be something else.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, no, you want to take up situation in regard to something.
[SPEAKER_00]: In regard to your body, in regard to your feelings, in regard to your mind, for that matter, which is almost like a situation, or in regard to the thoughts that arise, false adhipatānas.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you become peripherally aware of your body within, that's important, within,
[SPEAKER_00]: That situation is your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, even if you forget about your situation, the fact that that body is still there, that can become your anchor.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you get anchored through the anchor.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how mindfulness progresses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or expands.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you particularly think you have another body?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, then, yeah, then this body out there,
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, that becomes your situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, you don't have to do anything, for as long as your body is just out there, your situation is out there, and you're mindful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it doesn't require any attention.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because attention means attending something, which means whenever you attend something, there is peripheral.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is actual, there is peripheral.
[SPEAKER_00]: Always.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you give a hundred percent,
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is actually possible, as you can see.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't, like, give 100% of your attention to something, because that would mean you're fully absorbed in that thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there is always a background to whatever you're fully attending.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that background is always something that you're peripherally aware of.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just how things are ordered.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just the nature of the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you fully develop that knowledge,
[SPEAKER_00]: Means you can be fully attending whatever you want.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your mindfulness cannot latch.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there is always spiritual awareness.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's fully known.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why consciousness is to be understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the direction of consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's the way.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's the... way to abandon...
[SPEAKER_00]: It means that no matter how raging your body is, in terms of anger, or lust, or whatever else, well, now you learn how to see it indirectly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, seeing it indirectly means seeing it as not mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, there's a cold cut, kind of.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can choose to go into it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know you can.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unless when you become an anāgāmī, and then an arahant, whereby even the choice of going back into it is fully understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, even going back into it becomes inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: The choices.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, because of sensuality and anger.
[SPEAKER_00]: But they still have that, you know, the subtle.
[SPEAKER_00]: Claiming for presence, claiming for non-presence, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: For absence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it that the self is on the general level?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, self is usually where you don't look.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yes, self never appears as an object which you can look at.
[SPEAKER_00]: However, if you learn how to see things peripherally, then the general sense of self is seen peripherally, as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it has to... And, as I said, it's within the situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything is within the situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: It eventually appears in some.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it always appears in that negative manner.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the whole peripheral, the whole prospect of the peripheral, is a negative in regard to what you're used to looking in front of you, which is positive.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there is always a degree of negative in regard to everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why there's always a degree of self-perpetuation in regard to everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: But once you start abandoning actual emptiness, as mind, then that which used to be your Self, well, those things still keep manifesting, but now they are not mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, there is no more Self of mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I try to find the Self and then
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, you can't find it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can discern the phenomenon that's mine, that's me, that's I am, within the general situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, for another one, that just becomes like a shape of individual that he is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Phenomenological shape of there used to be me, mine, now it's just this individual.
[SPEAKER_01]: But things are establishments of mind, then, or something you do better, or you can do better.
[SPEAKER_00]: While being mindful of the situation, while having that proper attentional peripheral... Yeah, that's the direction for any establishment of mind, whether jhānas or anything, the Sīla practice, it's that, through that development of that peripheral.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because once you have that established, then you can establish other things, other particular things, like compassion or whatever, kindness.
[SPEAKER_00]: I see what you mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can be dwelling in it more particularly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can take a particular perception.
[SPEAKER_00]: Literally, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: To help undo things more, more faster.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because when you're established in the jhāna situation, you realize, okay, now I'm beyond griefs and joys in regard to the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you're in the state of that beyond, then, well, now I might as well, since you can, make that body which is not mine, which is already there, on its own, think things that are good for it, such as compassion and everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, when I'm not mindful, if I fall back, lapse, forget, get careless, fall back into the more wholesome environment that I might appropriate again as mine,
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you keep doing it, you keep doing it, you keep doing it, until eventually, for an hour, you can't even fall back anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's fully developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is how you can operate and exist like every other living being.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can't tell the difference externally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Could it be the Buddha?
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes people didn't recognize him.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes people, they were his followers, like that monk, who never met him.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the bar?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the bar, yeah, and they spent like ten years recognizing him.
[SPEAKER_00]: How could he?
[SPEAKER_00]: How could anybody, short of a Buddha, or an Arahant at least, or from... with great powers, recognize him?
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's nothing to do with external anyone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or very little.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, I saw this whole story about the description of how the Buddha's body was... Oh, yeah, it was in the 13... 32 or 36 months, yeah, I don't remember.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but it's hard to decide for that, because it just... it was like in every Indian religion, they have its... Yeah, the birth story.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And all sorts.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing to do with anything of significance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, the first person the Buddha met upon his enlightenment, when he saw, oh, wow, look, this monk is quite bright, his senses are clear, confidently walking, he looks like he might be enlightened.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he kind of suspected.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is quite a confident look the Buddha was emitting, like a great lion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he asked him, ah, whose, whose, whose instruction did you follow?
[SPEAKER_00]: He said, no one.
[SPEAKER_00]: I, I enlightened myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm fully enlightened by myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nobody is my teacher.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm my own dharma, the supreme leader.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what happens when I say, yeah, right, so be it.
Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Laugh at him who walked off.
[SPEAKER_01]: He'll beat you drunk.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, and that's what the Buddha realized.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, if he, if he, if he approaches this, because he could have said, yeah, I'm the greatest man in the world, because it will be factual.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's the greatest in, like, every realm.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just this world.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the extent of being the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_00]: So there was that.
[SPEAKER_00]: He could have said that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It wouldn't be a lie.
[SPEAKER_00]: It wouldn't be conceit.
[SPEAKER_00]: It wouldn't be nothing like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But because everybody else is clouded by their conceit, they could have not possibly seen it as anything other than conceit, which is exactly what this man... Oh, really?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, so be it, my friend.
[SPEAKER_00]: And walked off.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then they reformulated it and thought, well, maybe if I approach it something that they can all relate, which is suffering and freedom from
[SPEAKER_00]: Because when he went to the four disciples, when they asked him, again they saw, he looks like he might be alive, very confident in the way he moves and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So they... Oh, whose instructions did you follow?
[SPEAKER_00]: And he... yeah, but he just... well, there is suffering, there is fear.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whose instructions?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, there is suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: He just refused.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know, just listen what I'm talking about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stop asking those questions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Have you ever heard me speak like this?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, we didn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, then, be quiet and listen.